So imagine, you're in the supermarket,
حسنا تخيلوا , انكم في السوبرماركت .
you're buying some groceries,
تقومون بشراء بعض المواد الغذائية
and you get given the option
و يعطى لك الاختيار
for a plastic or a paper shopping bag.
بين كيس تسوق بلاستيكي و اخر من الورق
Which one do you choose if you want to do
ايهما ستختار اذا اردت ان تقعل
the right thing by the environment?
الشئ الصحيح نحو البيئة
Most people do pick the paper.
اكثر الناس سوف يختارون الكيس الورقي
Okay, let's think of why.
حسنا , لنفكر لماذا ؟
It's brown to start with.
اولا لانه بني .
Therefore, it must be good for the environment.
لذلك لابد انه جيد بالنسبة للبيئة .
It's biodegradable. It's reusable.
انه قابل للتحلل . و يمكن اعادة استخدامه
In some cases, it's recyclable.
في بعض الحالات ,و يمكن اعادة تدويره.
So when people are looking at the plastic bag,
لذلك عندما ينظر الناس الى الكيس البلاستيكي .
it's likely they're thinking of something like this,
من الارجح انهم يفكرون في شئ كهذا ,
which we all know is absolutely terrible,
و الذي يعرف جميعنا بانه شي فظيع للغاية
and we should be avoiding at all expenses
و اننا يجب ان نتفاداه في جميع الظروف
these kinds of environmental damages.
هذا النوع من الاضرار البيئية
But people are often not thinking
و لكن الناس لا يفكرون غالبا
of something like this,
بشئ كهذا
which is the other end of the spectrum.
و الذي هو الجزء الاخر من المعادلة
When we produce materials,
عندما ننتج المواد ,
we need to extract them from the environment,
يجب ان نستخرجهم من البيئة
and we need a whole bunch of environmental impacts.
ونحن بحاجة إلى مجموعة كاملة من الآثار البيئية.
You see, what happens is, when we need
ما يحدث اننا نحتاج
to make complex choices,
ان نقوم باختيارات معقدة
us humans like really simple solutions,
نحن البشر نحب الحلول البسيطة,
and so we often ask for simple solutions.
و لذالك غالبا نسأل عن الحلول البسيطة .
And I work in design.
و انا اعمل في مجال التصميم
I advise designers
اقدم المشورة الى المصممين
and innovators around sustainability,
و المبتكرين حول الحفاظ على البيئة ( الاستدامة البيئية )
and everyone always says to me, "Oh Leyla,
و الجميع دائما يقول لي " اوه ليلا
I just want the eco-materials."
نريد المواد البيئية فقط "
And I say, "Well, that's very complex,
و انا ارد قائلة " حسنا هذا معقد جدا ,
and we'll have to spend four hours talking about
وسوف يتوجب علينا ان نمضي اربعة ساعات بالتكلم عن
what exactly an eco-material means,
مالذي تعنيه عبارة مادة بيئية بالتحديد
because everything at some point
لان كل شي في لحظة ما
comes from nature,
يأتي من الطبيعة
and it's how you use the material
و كيفة استخدامكم للمادة
that dictates the environmental impact.
هو ما ياتي بالتأثير على البيئة
So what happens is, we have to rely
اذا ما يحصل هو , يجب ان نعتمد
on some sort of intuitive framework
نوع من الاساسات البديهية
when we make decisions.
عندا نتاخذ القرارات .
So I like to call that intuitive framework
لذا احب ان ادعو القرارات البديهية
our environmental folklore.
بفلكلورنا البيئي
It's either the little voice at the back of your head,
انما هو الصوت الصفير في موخرة روسكم
or it's that gut feeling you get
او ذالك الاحساس العميق الذي يأتيكم
when you've done the right thing,
عندما تقوم بفعل الشي الصحيح
so when you've picked the paper bag
فعدما اخذتم الكيس الورقي
or when you've bought a fuel-efficient car.
او عندما قمتم بشراء سيارة مقتصدة للوقود
And environmental folklore is a really important thing
و الفلكلور البيئي امر مهم جدا
because we're trying to do the right thing.
لاننا نحاول بفعل الشئ الصحيح
But how do we know if we're actually
و لكن كيف يمكننا ان نعرف اذا كنا حقا نقوم
reducing the net environmental impacts
بتقليل التأثير البيئي
that our actions as individuals and as professionals
التي تصرفاتنا كأقراد و كمحترفين
and as a society are actually having
و كمجتمع
on the natural environment?
تحدثه في البيئة الطبيعية
So the thing about environmental folklore is
وبالتالي فإن الشيء عن الفولكلور البيئي
it tends to be based on our experiences,
يميل الى ان يتمحور حول خبراتنا
the things we've heard from other people.
و الاشياء التي سمعناها من اناس اخرين
It doesn't tend to be based on any scientific framework.
لا تميل الى ان تكون مبنية على اي اسس علمية
And this is really hard, because we live
و هذا صعب للغاية لاننا نعيش
in incredibly complex systems.
في انظمة معقدة للغاية
We have the human systems
لدينا النظام البشري
of how we communicate and interrelate
الذي يدور حول كيف نتواصل و نتحد
and have our whole constructed society,
و نكون مجتمعنا الكامل المبني
We have the industrial systems, which is essentially the entire economy,
نمتلك انظمة صناعية و التي هي الاقتصاد بأكمله
and then all of that has to operate
و كل هذا يجب ان يشغل
within the biggest system,
ضمن النظام الاكبر
and, I would argue, the most important,
و انا اجادل بأن الشي الاكثر اهمية
the ecosystem.
النظم الإيكولوجية
And you see, the choices that we make
و كما ترون , الخيارات التي نتخذها
as an individual,
كأفراد
but the choices that we make
و الخيارات التي نتخذها
in every single job that we have,
في اي عمل نمتلكه
no matter how high or low you are in the pecking order,
مهما كانت ترتيبك في النظام الاجتماعي
has an impact on all of these systems.
لديها تأثير في كل هذه الانظمة
And the thing is that we have to find ways
و الامر المهم هو اننا يجب ان نجد طرق
if we're actually going to address sustainability
اذا اردنا ان نناقش استدامة
of interlocking those complex systems
النظم المعقدة المتشابكة
and making better choices that result
و ان نتخذ خيارات افضل تودي الى
in net environmental gains.
مكاسب بيئية كبيرة
What we need to do is we need to learn
ما يجب ان نفعله هو ان نتعلم
to do more with less.
ان نفعل الكثير بالقليل
We have an increasing population,
لدينا كثافة سكانية متزايدة
and everybody likes their mobile phones,
و كلنا يحب هاتفه النقال
especially in this situation here.
خاصة في هذا الموقف
So we need to find innovative ways of solving some of these problems that we face.
لذلك يجب ان نجد طرق مبتكرة لحل بعض هذه المشاكل التي نواجهها
And that's where this process called life cycle thinking comes in.
و هنا تاتي العمية التي تسمى تفكير دورة الحياة
So essentially, everything that is created
لذالك , اي شي يصنع
goes through a series of life cycle stages,
يمر عبر دورات حياة مختلفة
and we use this scientific process
ونحن نستخدم هذه العملية العلمية
called life cycle assessment,
و التي تسمى بتقيم دورة الحياة
or in America, you guys say life cycle analysis,
او كما انتم في امريكا تسمونها تحليل دورة الحياة
in order to have a clearer picture of how
لكي يكون لدينا صورة اكثر وضوحا عن لماذا
everything that we do in the technical part of those systems
كل شي نفعله في الجزء التقني الذي يتعلق بهذه الانظمة
affects the natural environment.
يؤثر في البيئية الطبيعية
So we go all the way back
لذلك نرجع الى
to the extraction of raw materials,
استخراج مواد الخام
and then we look at manufacturing,
ثم ننظر الى التصنيع
we look at packaging and transportation,
ننظر الى التغليف و النقل
use, and end of life,
الاستخدام و نهاية الحياة
and at every single one of these stages,
في كل مرحلة من هذه المراحل
the things that we do
الاشياء التي نفعلها
have an interaction with the natural environment,
تتداخل مع البيئة الطبيعية
and we can monitor how that interaction
و يمكن ان نراقب كيف ان التداخل
is actually affecting the systems and services
يؤثر في هذه الانظمة و الخدمات
that make life on Earth possible.
التي تجعل الحياة على الارض ممكنة
And through doing this,
و بواسطة فعل هذا
we've learned some absolutely fascinating things.
تعلمنا بعض الامور المثيرة
And we've busted a bunch of myths.
و دحضنا بعض الخرافات
So to start with, there's a word that's used a lot.
في بداية الامر , هنالك كلمة تستخم كثيرا
It's used a lot in marketing,
انها تستخم في مجال التسويق
and it's used a lot, I think, in our conversation
انها تستخدم كثيرا في محادثاتنا
when we're talking about sustainability,
عندما نتكلم عن الاستدامة البيئية ,
and that's the word biodegradability.
و هذه الكلمة هي التحلل البيولوجي
Now biodegradability is a material property;
الان التحلل البيولوجي هو خاصية المادة
it is not a definition of environmental benefits.
انها ليست تعريف للفوائد البيئية
Allow me to explain.
دعوني افسر لكم
When something natural,
في حالة وجود شيء طبيعي
something that's made from a cellulose fiber
شي تم صنعه من الياف السيليلوز
like a piece of bread, even, or any food waste,
مثل قطعة خبز , او حتى اي بقايا طعام
or even a piece of paper,
او حتى جزء من ورقة
when something natural ends up
عندما ينتهي جزء من الطبيعة
in the natural environment, it degrades normally.
في بيئة طبيعية , فأنه يتحلل طبيعيا .
Its little carbon molecules that it stored up
جزيئاته الكربونية التي خزنت
as it was growing are naturally released
في طور نموه الطبيعي تتحرر
back into the atmosphere as carbon dioxide,
الى الفضاء بشكل ثاني اوكسيد الكربون
but this is a net situation.
و لكن هذا الوضع الطبيعي
Most natural things
معظم الاشياء الطبيعية
don't actually end up in nature.
لا ينتهي بها الامر في الطبيعة
Most of the things, the waste that we produce, end up in landfill.
معظم الاشياء , الفضلات التي ننتجها , ينتهي بها الامر في مكبات النفايات
Landfill is a different environment.
ان المكبات بيئة مختلفة .
In landfill, those same carbon molecules
في المكبات , نفس جزيئات الكربون تلك
degrade in a different way,
تحلل بطريقة مختلفة
because a landfill is anaerobic.
لان المكب ( لا هوائي)
It's got no oxygen. It's tightly compacted and hot.
لا تحتوي على أوكسجين . انها مكدسة للغاية و شديدة الحرارة .
Those same molecules, they become methane,
نفس تلك الجزيئات تتحول الى ميثان ,
and methane is a 25 times more potent
و الميثان انه غاز الدفيئة الاكثر قوة بخمس و عشرين مرة
greenhouse gas than carbon dioxide.
من غاز ثاني اوكسيد الكربون
So our old lettuces and products
لذا خسنا القديم و منتجاتنا
that we have thrown out that are made
التي رميناها , و التي صنعت
out of biodegradable materials,
من المواد المتحللة بيئيا
if they end up in landfill,
اذا انتها بها الامر في المكبات
contribute to climate change.
يساهمو في التغير المناخي
You see, there are facilities now
كما تعلمون هنالك بعض االمرافق الان
that can actually capture that methane
حيث يستطيعوا ان يستخرجو الميثان
and generate power,
و ينتجو الطاقة
displacing the need for fossil fuel power,
و يستبدلوا حاجتنا لاستخدام طافة الوقود الاحفوري
but we need to be smart about this.
و لكن يجب ان نكون اذكياء
We need to identify how we can start to leverage
يجب ان نعرف كيف يمكننا ان نبدا في التأثير
these types of things that are already happening
في هذا الاشياء التي تحدث حاليا
and start to design systems and services
و البدء في تصميم انظمة و خدمات
that alleviate these problems.
تؤدي الى تخفيف هذه المشاكل
Because right now, what people do is they turn around and they say,
لان الان ما يفعله الناس هو انهم يقولون
"Let's ban plastic bags. We'll give people paper
" لنمنع الاكياس البلاستيكية . نعطي الناس االورق
because that is better for the environment."
لان هذا افضل للبيئة "
But if you're throwing it in the bin,
و لكن اذا رميتموه في سلة المهملات
and your local landfill facility
و مرفق مكبكم المحلي
is just a normal one,
غير متطور
then we're having what's called a double negative.
حينها سوف يكون لدنيا ما نسميه السلبي المضاعف
I'm a product designer by trade.
انا مصممة منتجات بمهنتي
I then did social science.
ثم درست علم الاجتماع
And so I'm absolutely fascinated
انني مبهورة للغاية
by consumer goods and how the consumer goods
من السلع الاستهلاكية و كيف ان السلع الاستهلاكية
that we have kind of become immune to
التي نملكها اصبحت محصنة ضد
that fill our lives
التي تملأ حياتنا
have an impact on the natural environment.
توثر في البيئة الطبيعية
And these guys are, like, serial offenders,
و هؤلاء الاشخاص , كالجناة المتسلسلين
and I'm pretty sure everyone in this room
انني متاكدة بأن كل شخص في الغرفة
has a refrigerator.
يمتلك ثلاجة .
Now America has this amazing ability
حاليا امريكا تمتلك قدرة مذهلة
to keep growing refrigerators.
في زيادة حجم الثلاجات
In the last few years, they've grown one cubic foot
في السنين القليلة الماضية , زادوا قدم مربع
on average, the standard size
في المتوسط , و الحجم القياسي
of a refrigerator.
للثلاجة
And the problem is, they're so big now,
و المشكلة انها كبيرة جدا لدرجة ان الان
it's easier for us to buy more food
اصبح من الاسهل ان نشتري طعام اكثر
that we can't eat or find.
و الذي لا نستطيع اكله و العثور عليه
I mean, I have things at the back of my refrigerator
اعني لدي بعض الاشياء في مؤخرة الثلاجة
that have been there for years, all right?
كانت هنالك منذ سنين اليس كذالك ؟
And so what happens is, we waste more food.
ما يحصل اننا ننبذر في طعام اكثر
And as I was just explaining, food waste is a problem.
و كما كنت افسر قبل قليل , بقايا الطعام مشكلة
In fact, here in the U.S., 40 percent
في الواقع هنا في الولايات المتحدة 40 في المئة
of food purchased for the home is wasted.
من الطعام المشترى للبيت يرمى
Half of the world's produced food is wasted.
نصف طعام العالم المنتج يرمى
That's the latest U.N. stats. Up to half of the food.
هذا تقرير الامم المتحدة الاحدث . نصف الطعام
It's insane. It's 1.3 billion tons of food per annum.
هذا جنون , انه 1.3 بليون طن من الطعام سنويا .
And I blame it on the refrigerator,
و انا اضع اللوم على الثلاجات
well, especially in Western cultures,
حسنا . الثقافات الغربية عموما
because it makes it easier.
لان هذا يزيد من السهولة
I mean, there's a lot of complex systems going on here.
اعني هناك الكثير من الانظمة المعقدة التي تجري حاليا
I don't want to make it so simplistic.
لا اري ان ابسط الامر جدا
But the refrigerator is a serious contributor to this,
و لكن الثلاجة مؤثر كبير لهذا
and one of the features of it
و واحدة من الخاصيات التي بها
is the crisper drawer.
انه درج تهشيش الخضار
You all got crisper drawers?
كلكم تملكون درجا لتهشيش الخضار
The drawer that you put your lettuces in?
الدرج الذي تضعون خسكم فيه
Lettuces have a habit of going soggy
الخس لديه القابلية بأن، يصبح رطبا
in the crisper drawers, don't they?
في درج الهشاشة , اليس كذالك ؟
Yeah? Soggy lettuces?
نعم ؟ خس رطب
In the U.K., this is such a problem
في الممكلة المتحدة يمثل هذا مشكلة لدرجة انه
that there was a government report a few years ago
كان هنالك تقرير حكومي قبل سنين
that actually said the second biggest offender
و الذي قال بأن اكبر ثاني مذنب
of wasted food in the U.K. is the soggy lettuce.
من الطعام الذي يرمى في المملكة المتحدة هو الخس الرطب
It was called the Soggy Lettuce Report.
لقد دعي تقرير الخس الرطب
Okay? So this is a problem, people.
حسنا ؟ انها مشكلة ايها الناس
These poor little lettuces are getting thrown out
يرمى هذا الخس المسكين
left, right and center because the crisper drawers
شمال , يمين , وسط لأن ادراج الهشاشة هذه
are not designed to actually keep things crisp.
لم تصمم لكي تبقي الخس رطبا
Okay. You need a tight environment.
اوكي يجب ان يكون هنالك بيئة مغلقة
You need, like, an airless environment
تحتاجون الى شيء مثل بيئة لا هواء فيها
to prevent the degrading that would happen naturally.
لكي تمنعو التحلل الذي كان ليحدث طبيعيا
But the crisper drawers, they're just a drawer
و لكن درج الهشاشة ليس سوى درجا
with a slightly better seal.
مزود بقفل افضل بنسبة ليست كبيرة
Anyway, I'm clearly obsessed.
على اي حال , انا مهوسة كما هو واضح
Don't ever invite me over because I'll just start going through your refrigerator
لا تدعونني الى منزلكم لأني سوف اذهب الى ثلاجاتكم
and looking at all sorts of things like that.
و انظرالى جميع الاشياء هذه
But essentially, this is a big problem.
ولكن أساسا، هذه مشكلة كبيرة.
Because when we lose something like the lettuce from the system,
لأننا عندما نفقد شيئا مثل الخس من النظام
not only do we have that impact I just explained at the end of life,
لن يكون لدينا فقط ذلك التأثير الذي بينته في نهاية الحياة
but we actually have had to grow that lettuce.
و لكننا توجب علينا ان نزرع الخس
The life cycle impact of that lettuce is astronomical.
تأثير دورة حياة الخس امر فلكي
We've had to clear land.
توجب علينا ان نخلي الاراضي
We've had to plant seeds, phosphorus,
و غرس البذور , الفسفور
fertilizers, nutrients, water, sunlight.
السمادات ,المواد الغذائية, الماء , ضوء الشمس
All of the embodied impacts in that lettuce
جميع تلك الاشياء الموجودة في الخس
get lost from the system,
تضيع من النظام ,
which makes it a far bigger environmental impact
و الذي يجعل هذا مؤثر اكبر في البيئة
than the loss of the energy from the fridge.
من ضياع الطاقة من الفريزر
So we need to design things like this far better
لذا يجب ان نصمم اشياء مثل هذا بشكل افضل جدا
if we're going to start addressing serious environmental problems.
اذا اردنا ان نواجه مشاكل بيئة خطيرة
We could start with the crisper drawer and the size.
يجب ان نبدأ في درج الهشاشة و الحجم
For those of you in the room who do design fridges,
لهؤلاء الاشخاص الذين يصممون الثلاجات
that would be great.
سوف يكون ذاك امر جيد
The problem is, imagine if we
المشكلة ان . تخيلو اذا نحن
actually started to reconsider how we designed things.
حقا بدانا في التفكير في كيفية تصميم الاشياء
So I look at the refrigerator as a sign of modernity,
لذا انظر الى الثلاجة كعلامة الحداثة ,
but we actually haven't really changed the design
و لكننا حقا لم نغير التصميم
of them that much since the 1950s.
كثيرا منذ الخمسينيات
A little bit, but essentially they're still big boxes,
قليلا و لكن في الاساس لا تزال صناديق كبيرة
cold boxes that we store stuff in.
صناديق باردة نخزن فيها الاشياء
So imagine if we actually really started
لذا تخيلو اذا حقا بدأنا
to identify these problems and use that
في تحديد المشاكل و استخدمنا ذلك
as the foundation for finding innovative and elegant
كاساس لايجاد حلول تصميم
design solutions that will solve those problems.
مبتكرة وأنيقة لحل تلك المشاكل
This is design-led system change,
هذا تغير النظام بواسطة التصميم
design dictating the way in which the system
التصيم يملي الطريقة و التي بواسطتها يكون النظام
can be far more sustainable.
يمكن أن يكون أكثر استدامة بكثير.
Forty percent food waste is a major problem.
اربعين بالمئة من فضلات من الطعام مشكلة كبيرة
Imagine if we designed fridges that halved that.
تخيلو اذا صممنا الثلاجات قسمت ذلك الى النصف
Another item that I find fascinating
منتج اخر اجده مبهر
is the electric tea kettle,
هو الغلاية الكهربائية
which I found out that
و ما اكتشفته
you don't do tea kettles in this country, really, do you?
انكم لا تستخدمون غلايات الشاي , في هذا البلد اليس كذالك ؟
But that's really big in the U.K.
و لكن استخدامها في المملكة المتحدة كبير
Ninety-seven percent of households
سبعة و تسعون في المئة من البيوت
in the United Kingdom own an electric tea kettle.
في المملكة المتحدة يمتلكون غلاية شاي كهربائية
So they're very popular.
لذالك هي مشهورة لللغاية
And, I mean, if I were to work with a design firm
و اعني اذا كنت لاعمل مع شركة تصميم
or a designer, and they were designing one of these,
او مصمم و كانو ليصمموا واحدة من هذه
and they wanted to do it eco,
و ارادو ان يجعلوها بيئية
they'd usually ask me two things.
كانو ليطلبوا مني شيئين
They'd say, "Leyla, how do I make it technically efficient?"
ليلا كيف تجعلي من هذه فعالة من الناحية التقنية ؟
Because obviously energy's a problem with this product.
لان الطاقة مشكلة كبيرة بالنسبة لهذ المنتج
Or, "How do I make it green materials?
او كيف تجعلينها مادة خضراء ؟
How do I make the materials green
كيف اجعل المادة خضراء (بيئية )
in the manufacturing?"
في التصنيع ؟
Would you ask me those questions?
لماذا تسئلو هذه الاسئلة
They seem logical, right? Yeah.
تبدو منطقية اليس كذالك ؟ نعم
Well I'd say, "You're looking at the wrong problems."
حسنا ما اقوله " انت تنظرون الى المشاكل الخاطئة
Because the problem is with use.
لان المشكلة هي في الإستخدام
It's with how people use the product.
تتعلق في كيفية استخدام الناس للمنتج
Sixty-five percent of Brits
خمس و ستون بالمئة من البريطانين
admit to over-filling their kettle
يعترفون بانهم يزيدو حجم الماء في غلاياتهم
when they only need one cup of tea.
عندما يحتاجون الى كوب واحد
All of this extra water that's being boiled
و جميع الماء الزائد الذي يغلى
requires energy, and it's been calculated
يحتاج الى الطاقة , و لقد تم حساب
that in one day of extra energy use
استخدام طاقة زائدة في يوم واحد
from boiling kettles
من الغلايات
is enough to light all of the streetlights
كافي لإضائة جميع اضواء الشوارع
in England for a night.
في المملكة المتحدة ليلا
But this is the thing.
و لكن هذا هو الشي
This is what I call a product-person failure.
الذي اسميه فشل المنتج/الشخص
But we've got a product-system failure going on with these little guys,
و لكن يوجد لدينا فشل المنتج/النظام و الذي يحدث حاليا للغلايات
and they're so ubiquitous, you don't even notice they're there.
و هي تنتشر في كل مكان لدرجة انك لا تستطيع ملاحظة وجودها
And this guy over here, though, he does. He's named Simon.
و هذا الشخص هنا , هو يميز و يدعى سيمون
Simon works for the national electricity company in the U.K.
سيمون يعمل لدى شركة الكهرباء القومية في المملكة المتحدة
He has a very important job of monitoring
لديه عمل مهم في مراقبة
all of the electricity coming into the system
جميع الكهرباء القادمة الى النظام
to make sure there is enough
للتاكد من ان هناك
so it powers everybody's homes.
طاقة كافية لجميع المنازل
He's also watching television.
و هو يشاهد التلفاز ايضا
The reason is because there's a unique
و السبب بان هناك ظاهرة
phenomenon that happens in the U.K.
فريدة تحدث في المملكة المتحدة
the moment that very popular TV shows end.
في اللحظة التي ينتهي فيها برنامج تلفاز مشهور
The minute the ad break comes on,
الدقيقة التي تبدا فيها استراحة الاعلانات
this man has to rush
يتوجب على هذا الرجل الاسراع
to buy nuclear power from France,
ليشتري طاقة نووية من فرنسا
because everybody turns their kettles on
لان الجميع يشغل غلايته
at the same time.
في نفس الزمن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
1.5 million kettles, seriously problematic.
1.5 غلاية إشكالية على محمل الجد.
So imagine if you designed kettles,
لذا تخيلو اذا صممتم الغلايات
you actually found a way to solve these system failures,
لقد وجدتم طريقة لحل فشل الانظمة
because this is a huge amount of pressure
لان الضغط الهائل
on the system,
على النظام
just because the product hasn't thought about the problem
لان المنتج لم يفكر في المشكلة
that it's going to have when it exists in the world.
التي سوف يواجها عندما يخرج الى العالم
Now, I looked at a number of kettles available on the market,
الان , نظرت على عدد من الغلايات المتوفرة في السوق
and found the minimum fill lines,
ووجدت خطوط حد الملئ الادنى
so the little piece of information that tells you
اذا تلك المعلومة البسيطة التي تخبركم
how much you need to put in there,
بالكمية التي تحتاجون ان تضعونها هنالك
was between two and a five-and-a-half cups of water
كانت بين كوبين الى خمسة اكواب و نصف من الماء
just to make one cup of tea.
فقط لصنع كوب واحد
So this kettle here is an example of one where
اذا هذه الغلاية هنا مثال .حيث
it actually has two reservoirs.
يوجد فيها خزاننين
One's a boiling chamber, and one's the water holder.
واحد حجرة غلي و الاخر حاملة للماء
The user actually has to push that button
المستخدم يجب حقا ان يضغط على الزر
to get their hot water boiled,
لجعل مائه يغلي
which means, because we're all lazy,
و الذي يعني , بما ان جميعنا كسولين
you only fill exactly what you need.
سوف تملئ تحديدا ما تحتاجه
And this is what I call behavior-changing products:
و هذا ما ادعوه منتجات مغيرة للسلوك
products, systems or services
منتجات , انظمة او خدمات
that intervene and solve these problems up front.
تتدخل و تحل تلك المشاكل .
Now, this is a technology arena,
الان , هذه ساحة تكنولوجيا
so obviously these things are quite popular,
لذالك تلك الاشياء مشهورة للغاية
but I think if we're going to keep
و لكن اعتقد اننا اذا سوف نستمر
designing, buying and using and throwing out
في تصميم و شراء و استخدام و رمي
these kinds of products at the rate we currently do,
ذالك النوع من المنتجات بنفس المعدل الحالي
which is astronomically high,
و الذي هو فلكي
there are seven billion people
هنالك سبعة مليار شخص
who live in the world right now.
يعيشون في العالم الان
There are six billion mobile phone subscriptions
هنالك ستة مليار اشتراك للهاتف النقال
as of last year.
من السنة الماضية
Every single year, 1.5 billion mobile phones
سنويا 1.5 مليار هاتف نقال
roll off production lines,
تنتج
and some companies report their production rate
و بعض الشركات تشير الى ان معدل انتاجها
as being greater than the human birth rate.
اكثر من معدل الولادة
One hundred fifty-two million phones were thrown out in the U.S. last year;
مئة و اثنان و خمسون هاتف رمي السنة الماضية في الولايات المتحدة
only 11 percent were recycled.
11 في المئة فقط اعيد تدويره
I'm from Australia. We have a population of 22 million -- don't laugh --
انا من استراليا تعدادنا السكاني 22 مليون نسمة  لا تضحكو
and it's been reported that 22 million phones
و لقد نشر بأن 22 مليون هاتف نقال
are in people's drawers.
موجودة في خزانات الناس
We need to find ways of solving the problems around this,
يجب ان نجد طرق لحل المشاكل حول هذا الموضوع
because these things are so complicated.
لان هذه الاشياء معقدة لدرجة انها
They have so much locked up inside them.
تحمل الكثيرمن الاسرار بداخلها
Gold! Did you know that it's actually cheaper now
الذهب ! هل تعلمون انه ارخص حاليا
to get gold out of a ton of old mobile phones
ان تحصل على الذهب من طن من الهواتف القديمة
than it is out of a ton of gold ore?
من ان تحصلون عليه من الذهب الخام
There's a number of highly complex and valuable
هناك عدد من المواد المعقدة و القيمة
materials embodied inside these things,
موجودة داخل هذه الاشياء
so we need to find ways of encouraging disassembly,
لذا يجب ان نجد طرق اخرى لتشجيع التفكيك
because this is otherwise what happens.
لأن هذا هو ما يحدث خلاف ذلك.
This is a community in Ghana,
هناك مجتمع في غانا
and e-waste is reported, or electronic waste
و الفضلات الالكترونية يبلغ عنها
is reported by the U.N.
بواسطة الامم المتحدة
as being up to 50 million tons trafficked.
الى ما يقارب 50 مليون طن
This is how they get the gold
هذا كيف يحصلون على الذهب
and the other valuable materials out.
و مواد قيمة اخرى
They burn the electronic waste
يحرقون الفضلات الالكترونية
in open spaces.
في فضائات مفتوحة
These are communities, and this is happening all over the world.
هذه مجتمعات و هذا يحصل في جميع انحاء العالم
And because we don't see the ramifications
و لأننا لا نرى تداعيات
of the choices that we make as designers,
الخيارات التي نتخذها كمصممين
as businesspeople, as consumers,
و كرجال اعمال و كمستهلكين
then these kinds of externalities happen,
حينها تحدث هذه العوامل الخارجية
and these are people's lives.
و هذه حياة الناس
So we need to find smarter, more systems-based,
يجب ان نجد طرق اكثر ذكاء , حلول مبتكرة
innovative solutions to these problems,
تعتمد على الانظمة لحل هذه المشاكل
if we're going to start to live sustainably within this world.
اذا اردنا ان نعيش في هذا العالم بطرق مستديمة
So imagine if, when you bought your mobile phone,
لذا تخيلو عندما اشتريتم هاتفكم النقال
your new one because you replaced your old one --
هاتفكم الجديد لانكم استبدلتم القديم
after 15 to 18 months is the average time
بعد 15 الى 18 شهر و هو الزمن المتوسط
that people replace their phones, by the way —
الذي يستبدل الناس فيه هواتفهم
so if we're going to keep this kind of expedient
لذلك اذا استمرينا في هذا النوع من التصرف
mobile phone replacing, then we should
تبديل هواتف اكثر , حينها يجب علينا
be looking at closing the loop on these systems.
ان نغلق الحلقة في تلك الانظمة
The people who produce these phones,
الاشخاص الذين ينتجون الهواتف
and some of which I'm sure are in the room right now,
و هؤلاء الذين وأنا متأكدة بوجودهم في هذه الغرفة
could potentially look at doing what we call closed-loop systems,
من المحتمل ان ينظروا إلى ما نسميه أنظمة الحلقات المغلقة
or product system services,
او خدمة انظمة المنتجات
so identifying that there is a market demand
لذالك الادراك بان هنالك طلب في السوق
and that market demand's not going to go anywhere,
و طلب السوق لن يزول
so you design the product to solve the problem.
لذالك صممو المنتج ليحل المشكلة
Design for disassembly, design for light-weighting.
صمم ليتفكك , صمم من اجل خفة الوزن
We heard some of those kinds of strategies
سمعنا بأن بعض هذه الاستراتجيات
being used in the Tesla Motors car today.
يستخدم في شركة ( تيسلا موتورز كار ) حاليا
These kinds of approaches are not hard,
هذا النوع من النهج ليس صعبا
but understanding the system
و لكن فهم الانظمة
and then looking for viable, market-driven
و من ثم النظرالى بدائل لطلب المستهلك
consumer demand alternatives
قابلة للتسويق
is how we can start radically altering
هو ما سوف يجعلنا نبدا في التغير الجذري
the sustainability agenda,
لخطط الاستدامة
because I hate to break it to you all:
لاني اكره ان اقول لكم جميعا
Consumption is the biggest problem.
الاستهلاك هو اكبر مشكلة
But design is one of the best solutions.
لكن التصميم واحد من افضل الحلول
These kinds of products are everywhere.
هذا النوع من المنتجات في كل مكان
By identifying alternative ways of doing things,
بتحديد طرق اخرى لعمل الاشياء
we can actually start to innovate,
نبدا حقا في الابتكار
and I say actually start to innovate.
و اقول بالقعل البدء في الابتكار
I'm sure everyone in this room is very innovative.
انا متأكدة بأن الجميع في هذه الغرفة مبتكر للغاية
But in the regards to using sustainability
ولكن في ما يتعلق باستخدام الاستدامة
as a parameter, as a criteria
كمعيار , كعلامة
for fueling systems-based solutions,
لتأجيج الحلول المعتمدة على النظم
because as I've just demonstrated with these simple products,
لان كما وضحت بواسطة هذه المنتجات البسيطة
they're participating in these major problems.
هم يشاركون في هذه المشاكل الهائلة
So we need to look across the entire life
لذا يجب ان ننظر الى جميع اجزاء الحياة
of the things that we do.
بالنسبة للاشياء التي نفعلها
If you just had paper or plastic --
اذا كان لديك ورق او بلاستيك
obviously reusable is far more beneficial --
من الواضح ان القابل لاعادة التدوير اكثر فائدة
then the paper is worse,
اذا فالورق اسوأ
and the paper is worse because it weighs
و الورق اسوا لانه يزن
four to 10 times more than the plastic,
اربعة الى عشرة اضعاف البلاستيك
and when we actually compare, from a life cycle perspective,
و عندما نقوم بالمقارنة من جانب دورة الحياة
a kilo of plastic and a kilo of paper,
كيلو من البلاستيك و كيلو من الورق
the paper is far better,
الورق افضل لكثير
but the functionality of a plastic or a paper bag
و لكن وظيفة الكيس البلاستيكي او الورقي
to carry your groceries home is not done with a kilo of each material.
في حمل مواد التبضع الى المنزل لا يتم بواسطة كيلو من المادتين
It's done with a very small amount of plastic
بل يتم بواسطة كمية قليلة من البلاستيك
and quite a lot more paper.
و لكن كمية اكبر من الورق
Because functionality defines environmental impact,
و لكن الوظيفة تحدد التأثير البيئي
and I said earlier that the designers always ask me for the eco-materials.
و قلت سابقا أن المصمين دائما يسألونني عن المواد البيئية
I say, there's only a few materials that you should completely avoid.
اقول لهم هنالك مواد قليلة يجب عليكم ان تتفادوها كليا
The rest of them, it's all about application,
و البقية تعتمد على طريقة استخدامها
and at the end of the day, everything we design and produce in the economy
و في نهاية المطاف كل شي نصممه و ننتجه في الاقتصاد
or buy as consumers is done so for function.
او نشتريه كمصممين كل من اجل الوظيفة
We want something, therefore we buy it.
نريد شيئا لذلك نشتريه
So breaking things back down and delivering
لذا تفكيك الاشياء و ايصال
smartly, elegantly, sophisticated solutions
حلول ذكية ,انيقة و متطورة
that take into consideration the entire system
تأخذ بعين الاعتبار النظام بأكمله
and the entire life of the thing, everything,
و حياة الشئ كله . جميع الاشياء
all the way back to the extraction through to the end of life,
رجوعا الى الاستخراج الى نهاية الحياة
we can start to actually find really innovative solutions.
نستطيع حينها ان نجد حلول مبتكرة حقا
And I'll just leave you with one very quick thing
و سوف اترككم بعد شيء سريع جدا
that a designer said to me recently who I work with, a senior designer.
مصمم خبير أعمل معه قال لي قريبا
I said, "How come you're not doing sustainability? I know you know this."
انا قلت " لماذا لا تعمل من اجل الاستدامة ؟ اعرف انك تعرف هذا "
And he said, "Well, recently I pitched a sustainability project to a client,
و قال هو , قريبا تجاهلت مشروعا عن الاستدامة الى عميل
and turned and he said to me,
التفت و قال لي
'I know it's going to cost less,
اعلم بانه سوف يكلف اقل
I know it's going to sell more,
اعلم بانه سوف يباع اكثر
but we're not pioneers, because pioneers have arrows in their backs.'"
ولكننا لسنا رواد لان الرواد يحملون سهما وراء ظهرهم
I think we've got a roomful of pioneers,
اعتقد بأن لدينا غرفة مليئة بالرواد
and I hope there are far more pioneers out there, because we need to solve these problems.
و امل بان هنالك الكثير من الرواد لاننا يجب ان نحل هذه المشاكل
Thank you.
شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
( تصفيق)